SUSAN NJERI MAINA

DATA SCIENTIST

<u>suemnjeri@gmail.com</u> +254 724 793817

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/suemnjeri
GitHub: https://github.com/suemnjeri
Medium: https://suemnjeri.medium.com/

PROFILE

Self-motivated data analyst who is passionate about solving problems using data and establishing systems that increase operational efficiencies. Advanced knowledge in Python, QuickBooks, and Microsoft Excel having implemented a record-keeping system for a real-estate company. Demonstrates exceptional operational and managerial skills with over four years of experience managing people in the hospitality industry and the commercial cleaning sector.

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

- Python
- R
- SQL
- Pandas
- Matplotlib
- Numpy
- Seaborn
- Scikit-learn
- ggplotMs Excel
- Quickbooks
- Java

- Git
- GitHub
- Data mining
- Data modeling
- Data visualization
- Data extraction and analysis
- Team player
- Stakeholder management
- Interpersonal skills
- Technical writing
- Power BI

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Science: Food Science and Nutrition Jomo Kenyatta University Of Agriculture And Technology (Jkuat), Thika, Kenya (2006 – 2009)

Software Development Diploma (Java and Database management) Digital Age Institute, Nairobi Kenya (2011 – 2012)

PROFESSIONAL COURSES

Data Scientist with Python track Datacamp (Jan 2022 – Present)

Data Science NanoDegree Udacity (2021 – Present)

Machine Learning Accelerator
Elite Data Science Academy (Oct-Dec 2020)

ICDL Certificate (International Computer Driving Licence)
Computer Programming Certificate
Web design certificate
Institute of Advanced Technology, Nairobi Kenya (2005, 2010)

PROJECTS

Exploratory Data Analysis (EDA):

- Explored a Housing dataset using Pandas, matplotlib, and seaborn. The target feature was 'price', a numeric feature.
 - Analyzed the data to understand its structure and the nature of its variables.
 - Identified variables that required transformation or had outliers.
 - Determined missing values that required imputation.
 - Investigated the relationships between the features particularly with the target feature.
 - Outlined the entire workflow in a blog post on medium.com.
- 2. Explored an HR analytics dataset to accomplish the above. The target was categorical (binary) hence required slightly different procedures.
 - Used crosstabs and count plots to investigate the distribution of the target among other categorical variables.

EDA, Cleaning, and visualization:

- Analyzed the Stack overflow 2020 survey data and answered three age-related questions using the visualizations.
- 4. Analyzed my articles' performance on medium to find the qualities of the best-performing articles.

Machine learning

- 5. Used Pandas, NumPy, and sci-kit-learn to compare the performance of three regression algorithms.
 - Simulated a dataset using pandas and Numpy
 - Implemented and compared how well 3 regression models of differing complexities predicted unseen data. The models were linear regression (least complex), decision tree, and random forest (most complex).

COMPETITIONS ON ZINDI

- 1. Used R statistical language to analyse the African Financial Inclusion dataset and utilised a Random forest to predict individuals likely to have or use to a commercial bank account. Finished at position 11
- 2. Analysed the Sendy logistics dataset and implemented a cat boost regression model to predict the estimated time of delivery of orders. Finished at position 11.
- 3. Was part of a team of 3 where we implemented a Time series Forecasting model to predict the number of incoming calls that Childline Kenya call center will receive per hour per day. We applied a weighted average on 3 models: lightGBM, catboost and XGBoost and finished in 2nd place.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Records Manager for tenants Faidi Properties Limited, Nairobi March 2018 – Present

- Implemented a record-keeping system for maintaining the running accounts of tenants for a real estate company using both QuickBooks and Ms Excel.
- Created tenants monthly and processed payments.
- Generated QuickBooks reports for monthly invoices, payments, and balances.
- Implemented a Python script for consolidating the above reports into one. The script loads the data, cleans it, merges the sets by the house number, and returns a single report containing each tenant's monthly transactions. This report was shared with stakeholders and the property manager who followed up with late payments.
- Analyzed historical data and identified high-risk tenants with a history of poor payments and prepared warning letters to prompt them into action.
- Prepared and printed monthly account statements for each tenant.

December 2020 - Present

- Wrote 26 articles about Data Science beginner tutorials and concepts on medium.com.
- Received top-writer tag two times in the area of data science content.
- Researched on topics, analyzed different datasets, and presented my findings in blog posts on topics such as exploratory data analysis, data cleaning, Pandas, Numpy, and control flow structures.
- Created Git repositories on GitHub to showcase the code and shared the links in the respective blogs.

Operations manager Woojoo Restaurant, Nairobi August 2017 – December 2019

- Lobbied for, sourced, and installed the SambaPOS point of sale system for ease of operations. This increased efficiency, reduced pilferage, and informed better business decisions using the data collected.
- Created a SambaPOS manual and regularly trained the team on the same.
- Developed and maintained the following Excel spreadsheets that were updated daily:
 - o Inventory spreadsheet to track the items received from suppliers, production items issued from the store, amounts produced in the kitchen, and items sold.
 - An 'accounts payable' spreadsheet to effectively track invoices and pay bills.
 - A cash management spreadsheet to balance daily cash transactions such as sales, banking, withdrawals and expenses.
- Worked with the team to develop operational manuals and checklists for the different restaurant departments (Waiters, cooks, and stewards). This ensured that all activities were standardized for everyone resulting in efficient workers and reducing labor costs because we let go of redundant workers.
- Interviewed, vetted, and trained new employees through manuals and on-the-job training.
- Attended and chaired meetings with fellow stakeholders on strategies for business growth.
- Maintained a very low staff turn-over through incentives such as friendly working hours, paid leave
 days, appraisals, brainstorming, and team building sessions to encourage communication between all
 team members, and instilling a sense of ownership in every employee by encouraging creativity and
 self-responsibility.
- Oversaw and approved the marketing strategies and activities in our social media accounts.

Site Manager Chania Cleaners Limited, Nairobi Jan 2011 – Jan 2013

- Supervised the cleaning operations of 4 Commercial banks (Equity banks) within Nairobi City, each with a team of five cleaners.
- Developed an attendance schedule to each branch for one hour daily where I checked the cleanliness status of the banking hall and back-of-house, talked to the customer representative in charge of cleanliness, and met with my team for a progress check.
- Liaised with the bank's customer care representative on cleaning schedules detailing the different areas to clean, and when to clean them.
- Ensured that daily checklists and attendance schedules were available.
- Allocated employees to appropriate areas based on their skills, experiences and, personalities.
- Interviewed, recruited and trained new employees through rigorous 2-week training at our company headquarters. Here, they learned about company policies and received hands-on training on good cleaning practices and how to use the equipment.
- Maintained amicable relations between all parties and resolved conflicts.
- Conducted site visits for potential new commercial jobs and wrote reports on my findings. This supported the tender application process when quoting how much to charge for the job.

Data Entry Clerk and Logistics Intern
Davis and Shirtliff Company Ltd, Nairobi
April – June 2011

- Created a report template using MS Excel for tabulating truck drivers' expenses, balances, and other trip details of long-distance trips to regional branches.
- Prepared weekly reports for the drivers that I passed on to my supervisor for approval and authorization of any cash refunds.
- Used MS Navision to order, invoice, and update the inventory of store items.

Food Lab Testing Attaché (Intern) Kenya Bureau of Standards, Nairobi Jan – March 2009

- Supported teams in the food, microbiology, agricultural, and organic chemistry laboratories in conducting chemical and microbial analysis using procedures like titration, mass spectrum analysis, and preparation and inoculation of media cultures.
- Followed Standard Operating Procedures to conduct tests and analyze samples to ascertain adherence to prescribed government standards.
- Recorded the results in Ms Excel and forwarded them to the head lab technician to write a final report approving or rejecting the product.
- Undertook general laboratory housekeeping to ensure all the pending and completed samples were well organized, labeled with company and date, and work surfaces and equipment were clean.

VOLUNTEER

Media Screen Projector OneTribe Church, Nairobi 2018 – Present

- Organized the text and media from the different participants such as songs, notices, and sermon notes.
- Uploaded the said media into the pro-presenter software and customized each section as required.
- Projected the media onto the screen on cue to ensure the audience kept up with the lyrics, notices, and sermon flow.
- Trained new volunteers on how to use the software and the requirements of a good projection sequence.

Tax returns officer – VAT, NHIF, PAYE and NSSF Acacia Traders Oct 2021 – Present

- Summed up all the monthly sales and expenses for the company, submitted the figures into the KRA Excel template and website, and generated the monthly tax report.
- Generated the NHIF, PAYE and NSSF monthly reports using the employee's salaries and other details, and submitted them to the manager who made the payments and ensured compliance with the Government's regulations.

ACTIVITIES

- Successful participant of the 1st Zindi Mentorship Programme in 2020.
- Member of the following local communities:
 - Nairobi Women in Machine Learning and Data Science
 - AlSaturday Nairobi
 - A4Ayub Hands-on-labs